<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Erastus Junior. Or, A fatal blovv to the clergies pretensions to divine right. In a solid demonstration, by principles, forms of ordination, canon-laws, acts and ordinances of Parliament, and other publique acts, instruments, records, and proceedings, owned by themselves, that no bishop, nor minister, (prelatical, or Presbyterian) nor presbytery (classical, or national) hath any right or authority to preach, ... in this nation, from Christ, but onely from the Parliament. In two parts: the one demonstrating it to an episcopal, the other to a Presbyterian minister. By Josiah Web, Gent. a serious detester of the dregs of the Antichristian hierarchy yet remaining among us.</title>
            <author>Lewgar, John, 1602-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88083</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1831</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1010_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202720</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862915</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862915</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168744</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88083)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168744)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 150:E1010[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Erastus Junior. Or, A fatal blovv to the clergies pretensions to divine right. In a solid demonstration, by principles, forms of ordination, canon-laws, acts and ordinances of Parliament, and other publique acts, instruments, records, and proceedings, owned by themselves, that no bishop, nor minister, (prelatical, or Presbyterian) nor presbytery (classical, or national) hath any right or authority to preach, ... in this nation, from Christ, but onely from the Parliament. In two parts: the one demonstrating it to an episcopal, the other to a Presbyterian minister. By Josiah Web, Gent. a serious detester of the dregs of the Antichristian hierarchy yet remaining among us.</title>
                  <author>Lewgar, John, 1602-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed, and are to be sold by Livewell Chapman at the signe of the Crown in Popeshead Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Josiah Web = John Lewgar.</note>
                  <note>Bound with Thomason items dated 1659.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou: 21 1659"; with a caret between "Web," and "gent.", and written above the text "a Papist &amp; livinge amongst us:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Apostolic succession --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168744:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Eraſtus Junior.</p>
            <p>OR, A FATAL BLOW TO THE CLERGIE'S Pretenſions to DIVINE RIGHT.</p>
            <p>In a ſolid Demonſtration, By Principles, Forms of Ordination, Canon-Laws, Acts and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Parliament, and other publique Acts, Inſtruments, Records, and Proceedings, owned by themſelves, THAT No <hi>Biſhop,</hi> nor <hi>Miniſter,</hi> (Prelatical, or Presbyterian) nor <hi>Presbytery</hi> (Claſſical, or National) hath any <hi>Right</hi> or <hi>Authority</hi> to <hi>Preach,</hi> (and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, much leſs, to Officiate in the publique Worſhip, miniſter Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, demand Tythes, ordain Paſtors, inflict Cenſures, or exerciſe any other act of <hi>Simple,</hi> and much leſs of <hi>Governing</hi> Juriſdiction,) in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but onely from the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In two parts: the one demonſtrating it to an <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> the other to a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Miniſter.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Joſiah Web,</hi> Gent. a ſerious deteſter of the Dregs of the Antichriſtian Hierarchy yet remaining among us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Livewell Chapman</hi> at the Signe of the Crown in <hi>Popeshead Alley,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:168744:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:168744:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>THere hath been much debate a long time betwixt the <hi>Prelatical</hi> and <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi> Clergy, which of them hath <hi>Divine Right</hi> (or <hi>Authority from Chriſt</hi>) to preach, miniſter Sacraments, ordain Paſtors, inflict Cenſures, and exerciſe other Acts of Spiritual Juriſdiction in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: whereas the plain truth is, neither of them hath any from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but onely from the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This truth I ſhall demonſtrate in the enſuing Diſcourſe, by their own Principles, forms of Ordination, Acts (or Ordinances) of Parliament, and other publique Acts, Inſtruments, and Records owned by themſelves. And in regard one of my means of proof is to be from their own Principles, I ſhall alledge divers things as truths, which are not ſo in my opinion, but onely in theirs againſt whom I urge them, and therefore alſo I ſhall in urging of them uſe their own terms.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the Demonſtration will be more expedite, and clear, in one of theſe Acts ſingly, then in ſo many together; and the confuting their Divine Right as to any one of them, will in conſequence confute it in all the reſt (becauſe they all hang by one ſtring;) and <hi>Preaching</hi> is the firſt and leaſt act of Juriſdiction, and ſo the proof againſt that, will prove more ſtrongly againſt all the reſt: therefore I ſhall inſiſt onely upon that of <hi>preaching,</hi> and demonſtrate, that no Miniſter ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Impoſition of hands, and conſtituted a Paſtor, whether it hath been by any of the late Biſhops, or a Claſſical Presbytery, hath any <hi>authority</hi> (by which I mean, power to exerciſe the Office lawfully) ſo much as to <hi>preach</hi> (by which I mean, teaching Gods word by way of Office) to any creature in this Nation, from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (that is, by any <hi>bene placitum,</hi> or will of his, by him revealed, or any means, or ordinance by him inſtituted to that end,) but onely from the <hi>Parliament,</hi> (originally under God, as author of Nature onely.)</p>
            <p>And my end in it, is,</p>
            <p>Firſt, to unbeguile the common people, in their believing their Miniſters as <hi>men of God,</hi> and <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt,</hi> and their teaching, as <hi>Gods word,</hi> becauſe of their being Ordained by Biſhops, or a Presbytery; and villifying all others not ſo Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, by the nick name of <hi>Tub-preachers:</hi> by making it appear, that there is not the meaneſt Teacher in the Land, allowed by the State, or deputed by a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but is a Teacher <hi>ſent,</hi> and a <hi>man of God,</hi> and <hi>Miniſter of Chriſt,</hi> as much as the Reverendſt Biſhop or Miniſter of them all; and his teaching, is as
<pb facs="tcp:168744:3"/>
truly <hi>the word of God,</hi> as the beſt of theirs is; that is, when he holds forth a Text of Scripture, or other revealed truth; and the the beſt of theirs is no more, or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to vindicate the Authority of the Parliament, in what they have done in aboliſhing Epiſcopacy, and ſeveral branches of it, or ſhall hereafter think fit to do, in aboliſhing the yet remaining branches of it, (Impoſition of hands, Tythes, Preſentations, Claſſes, Synods, National Miniſtery, Directory, &amp;c.) and impow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ering every Congregation to depute their own Paſtor: by making it appear, there is no Miniſter, Prieſt, Biſhop, Claſſis, or Synod, in this Land, hath or (ſince the Reformation of Religion by <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth) ever had any authority to Ordain Paſtors, demand Tythes, licenſe Preachers, or ſo much as to <hi>preach,</hi> but what he or they have or had originally (under God) from the Parliament; which therefore by the ſame Authority whereby it eſtabliſhed them, may when it pleaſes diſſolve them, without any ones juſt complaint at the Authority.</p>
            <p>And now then to go in hand with what I have undertaken, and to proceed againſt them ſeverally, beginning firſt with the elder of the two, the Prelatical <hi>Miniſter,</hi> (or <hi>Prieſt,</hi> as he loves to be called.)</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:168744:3"/>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The firſt Part. Demonſtrating to an Epiſcopal Prieſt, that he hath no authority to Preach, from Chriſt, but onely from the Parliament.</head>
               <p>SIr, I ſhall ſuppoſe your Caſe the beſt can be ſuppoſed of any Prelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Miniſter in <hi>England, viz.</hi> That <hi>William Lawd,</hi> late (commonly called) Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> being a true Biſhop <hi>Ordine,</hi> (or in power of Epiſcopal Order) and as much as the King and all the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in <hi>England</hi> could make him, lawful Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury, Ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> you a true Prieſt, and afterward gave you <hi>Miſſion</hi> to the Church of <hi>N.</hi> within his Dioceſs, (that is, <hi>Inſtituted</hi> you Rector or Paſtor of it, and <hi>Licenſed</hi> you to preach in that Congregation.) And I ſay, that in this Caſe, <hi>you have no authority to preach to that Congregation, from Chriſt, but onely from the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi> And I make it good by this Argument.</p>
               <p>You have no authority from Chriſt to preach to that Congregation, but what you have, either by your <hi>Ordination,</hi> or by your <hi>Miſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But you have no authority to preach to that Congregation, by your <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination;</hi> and none from him, but from the Parliament onely; by your <hi>Miſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore you have none from him, but onely from the Parliament.</p>
               <p>The <hi>major</hi> is ſuppoſed in the Caſe: nor is there any other ordinary way imaginable, and you pretend not to extraordinary.</p>
               <p>The firſt part of the <hi>minor [That you have no authority to preach to that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, by your Ordination,]</hi> I prove from the form of your Ordination, which was this. The Biſhop, with the other Prieſts preſent, laying their hands upon you, the Biſhop ſaid theſe words to you, [<hi>Receive the Holy Ghoſt: whoſe ſins thou forgiveſt, they are forgiven: whoſe ſins thou retaineſt, they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained: and be thou a faithful diſpenſer of the Word of God, and of his holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments. In the Name of the Father,</hi> &amp;c.] After which the Biſhop deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Bible to you, ſaid theſe words <hi>[Take thou authority to preach the Word, and to miniſter the holy Sacraments, in this Congregation, where thou ſhalt be ſo appointed]</hi> So, what authority you have by your <hi>Ordination,</hi> muſt be given you by the one of theſe words. Now,</p>
               <p>Firſt, that the former words at the Impoſition of hands [<hi>Receive the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt,</hi> &amp;c.] gave you none, is manifeſt; becauſe thoſe words, being <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental,</hi>
                  <note n="(a)">We deny not Ordination to be a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, though it be not one of thoſe two, which are generally neceſſary to ſalvation. <hi>Biſh. of</hi> Derr. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>p. 97.</hi>
                  </note> (that is, giving a <hi>grace</hi> (or free gift of the Holy Ghoſt) from Chriſt immediately, to preach and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168744:4"/>
Sacraments;) what grace they gave you, they gave you to all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations in the world alike, as much to every one as to any one; becauſe they propagated to you the ſame power as Chriſt gave to his Apoſtles, when he ſaid to them, [<hi>As my father ſent me, ſo I ſend you. Receive the Holy Ghoſt; Whoſe ſins you remit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Preach the Goſpel to every creature,</hi> &amp;c.] whence it is, that being once Ordained, you are capable to preach and miniſter Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to any creature or Congregation in the world, by meer <hi>Miſſion</hi> onely, without a new Ordination. If then the grace they gave you were <hi>Authority</hi> to preach and miniſter Sacraments to that Congregation; theſe abſurdities would inevitably follow.</p>
               <p n="1">1. You would be a Paſtor <hi>Apoſtolique,</hi> or ſuch a one as the Apoſtles were, that is, a <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> one, created by Chriſt <hi>immediately,</hi> and conſequently a <hi>ſupreme</hi> one, (ſubject to no mortal ſuperior, in the exerciſe of your juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction:) which would utterly overthrow all your Hierarchy.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The next words, at the delivery of the Bible to you <hi>[Take thou autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to preach in the Congregation where thou ſhalt be appointed:]</hi> would be, 1. Vain, and abſurd, to give authority given before. 2. Retractatory of the former. 1. To qualifie the authority, given before abſolute. 2. To ſuſpend it to a future condition, or event, poſſible never to be; when it was given be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, abſolutely, and in preſent.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Your <hi>Miſſion</hi> afterward to that Church of <hi>N.</hi> would have been, 1. An act vain and arrogant in the Biſhop, to authorize you to preach, and to one Congregation; after Chriſt himſelf had authorized you, both to that, and to any other. 2. A proceeding injurious to all other Prieſts, to Inſtitute you Paſtor of that as your <hi>proper</hi> charge, with this priviledge, that none might miniſter a Sacrament, or ſo much as preach there without your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: when Chriſt had Inſtituted every one of them Paſtor of it, in <hi>common</hi> with you; for if, by the words of Ordination, he authorized you to that Cure; by the ſame words he authorized every other Prieſt in the world to it, as much as you. 3. A proceeding injurious to your own ſelf. 1. To ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of a Paſtorſhip from the Biſhop, and ſo to hold it of him, as your meſne Lord, liable to be ſuſpended, or deprived of it at any time, by ſentence of his Court; when you had a right to hold it immediately of the Lord Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramont, and ſo without ſubjection or ſervice to any but him. 2. To accept from him the Paſtorſhip of one Cure, and that none of the beſt in <hi>England,</hi> when Chriſt had authoriſed you to any Cure in the land, or in the world, where you would pleaſe to undertake it.</p>
               <p>The Church of Rome therefore (whoſe apes you are in this right of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and whoſe ſcholars in your doctrine of its being a Sacrament,) doth not hold, that the qualifying grace (or, as they call it, <hi>Character</hi>) given by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168744:4"/>
Ordination is any <hi>authority,</hi> but a meer <hi>power</hi> to exerciſe lawfully ſuch an Office, when authority ſhall be given for it by <hi>Miſſion.</hi> And if you will avoid theſe abſurdities, you muſt ſay, that no <hi>authority,</hi> but this <hi>power</hi> onely was given you by theſe firſt words, <hi>[Receive the Holy Ghoſt, &amp;c.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, that the next words, at the delivery of the Bible to you <hi>[Take thou authority, &amp;c.]</hi> gave you no authority to preach in that Congregation of <hi>N.</hi> is manifeſt from the words themſelves, becauſe they authorized you onely as to <hi>ſuch Congregation where you ſhould be appointed:</hi> which you were not then in that Church of <hi>N.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you ſay, theſe words gave you your authority to preach in any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation where you ſhould be appointed, and your appointing in that of <hi>N.</hi> onely determined the <hi>place,</hi> or aſſigned you a <hi>matter</hi> or <hi>ſubject</hi> whereon to exerciſe it: I ask, whether after theſe words, <hi>[Take thou authority, &amp;c.]</hi> and afore your appointing in that Church of <hi>N.</hi> you had a power (in your own right, without asking the Paſtors conſent) to preach lawfully in that Church of <hi>N.</hi> I ſuppoſe you will not, dare not, ſay you had: for then your <hi>appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> to it ſignified nothing; and then every Prieſt would be a lawful Paſtor to every flock, where and when he pleaſed; and all your Hierarchy (which ſubſiſts in the diſtinction of Paſtors and Flocks) would fall to the ground. And if you ſay, you had no ſuch power; you grant what I ſay, that theſe words gave you no <hi>authority</hi> to preach in that Congregation; but your <hi>appointment</hi> (or, as I call it, your <hi>miſſion</hi>) did not only determine the <hi>place,</hi> or aſſign you a <hi>matter</hi> or <hi>ſubject</hi> whereon to exerciſe the authority afore given you, but gave you your firſt <hi>authority</hi> there. And conſequently, though the Biſhop ſaid to you, <hi>[Take authority, &amp;c.]</hi> he could not poſſibly mean by <hi>authority,</hi> any more then a <hi>power</hi> to preach lawfully in any place where you ſhould be appointed.</p>
               <p>If you ſay, <hi>that</hi> power was given you in the words afore, and ſo would be vainly given you again here; I grant your inference: for though I argue va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidly from your form of Ordination, againſt you who approve it, I who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it not, am not concerned to defend it. So I hope I have ſufficiently proved the firſt part of my <hi>Minor, [That you have no Authority to preach to that Congregation of</hi> N. <hi>by your Ordination.</hi>]</p>
               <p>The ſecond part of it, <hi>[That you have none from Chriſt, (but onely from the Parliament) by your Miſſion:]</hi> I thus make good.</p>
               <p>If he who gave you your Miſſion had no authority from Chriſt (but onely from the Parliament) to give it you, you have no authority from Chriſt, but onely from the Parliament, by your Miſſion.</p>
               <p>But he who gave you your Miſſion, had no authority from Chriſt (but onely from the Parliament) to give it you.</p>
               <p>Therefore you have no authority from Chriſt (but onely from the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) by your Miſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:168744:5"/>The ſequel of the <hi>major</hi> is evident in the terms.</p>
               <p>The <hi>minor</hi> is thus proved.</p>
               <p>If <hi>William Lawd</hi> had authority from Chriſt to give you Miſſion, it muſt be, either as he was a Biſhop <hi>Ordine,</hi> or as he was a Biſhop <hi>Officio;</hi> that is, as he was <hi>Archbiſhop of Canterbury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But he had no authority to give you Miſſion, as he was a Biſhop <hi>Ordine,</hi> nor from Chriſt (but onely from the Parliament) as he was Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore he had no authority from Chriſt (but onely from the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) to give you Miſſion.</p>
               <p>The ſequel of the <hi>major</hi> I cannot ſuppoſe will be denied, becauſe no third ordinary way is imaginable. And you cannot ſay he had it in both reſpects joyntly, if (as will appear in proof of the <hi>minor</hi>) he had none at all, as he was a Biſhop <hi>Ordine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt part of the <hi>minor [That he had no authority to give you Miſſion, as he was a Biſhop Ordine]</hi> is manifeſt; becauſe the giving Miſſion, is an act of compleat Jurisdiction, which he had not as he was a Biſhop <hi>Ordine</hi> (no more in <hi>Canterbury,</hi> then he had in <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> or no more then the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> had in <hi>Canterbury.</hi>) And the Stile, in his Inſtrument, whereby he Inſtituted, and Licenſed you <hi>[William, by Divine Providence, Archbiſhop of Canterbury;]</hi> ſhewes, he Inſtituted and Licenſed you, not as he was a Biſhop <hi>Ordine,</hi> but as <hi>Archbiſhop of Canterbury:</hi> which he might have been (ſufficiently, to the Inſtituting and Licenſing you in that Church,) although he had not been ſo much as a Deacon <hi>Ordine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond part of it <hi>[That he had no authority from Chriſt, but onely from the Parliament, as he was Archbiſhop of Canterbury]</hi> is thus proved.</p>
               <p>He was no Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> by authority from Chriſt, but onely of the Parliament.</p>
               <p>Therefore he had no authority from Chriſt, but onely from the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as he was Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Conſequence is evident, The Antecedent, I prove thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Matthew Parker</hi> (the firſt Proteſtant Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi>) was no Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> by authority from Chriſt, but onely of the Parliament.</p>
               <p>Therefore <hi>Will. Lawd</hi> was no Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> by authority from Chriſt, but onely of the Parliament.</p>
               <p>The Conſequence I ſuppoſe will be granted me: becauſe <hi>Matth. Parker</hi> was Confirmed and Conſecrated, in all the ſame form, and by all the ſame authority, as <hi>Will. Lawd</hi> was: and he being the firſt Proteſtant Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> (and conſequently one, and the chief, in the Confirming and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168744:5"/>
Conſecrating of thoſe by whoſe Succeſſors <hi>William Lawd</hi> was Confirmed and Conſecrated) was the neceſſary <hi>pipe</hi> or <hi>channel,</hi> for conveying Divine Authority from Chriſt to <hi>William Lawd;</hi> and ſo muſt have his authority from Chriſt firſt afore <hi>William Lawd</hi> could have any by him.</p>
               <p>The Antecedent (which is indeed the onely difficult part of my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) I prove from the form of creating him Archbiſhop, which was this. The See being void, by the death of Cardinal <hi>Pool,</hi> the Dean and Chapter petitioned the Queen for her Licence to chuſe their Archbiſhop, which ſhe granting, ſent with it a Letter, nominating to them <hi>Matthew Parker</hi> for the man; and him they were bound to chuſe, under a Premunire. The Election being made, and certified into the Chancery, there iſſued out a Commiſſion under the great Seal to ſeven Biſhops, aſſigned by the Queen, commanding and authorizing them, or any four of them, to <hi>Confirm</hi> the election, and to <hi>Conſecrate</hi> him. This four of them did. And his <hi>Conſecration</hi> being certified by them into the Chancery, there iſſued out a Writ to the Dean and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter, commanding and authorizing them to <hi>Inſtall</hi> (or as they called it, to <hi>Inthronize</hi>) him: that is, to put him into the <hi>actual poſſeſſion</hi> of his Office and Dignity. After which he enjoyed his <hi>Spiritualties,</hi> (that is, all Spiritual Juriſdiction pertaining to that See.) And then iſſued a Writ out of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer to the Sheriff to reſtore to him the <hi>Temporalties,</hi> (which at the death of any Biſhop were uſed to be ſeized into the Prince's hands.)</p>
               <p>This was the whole form, from firſt to laſt, of creating him Archbiſhop: which (as you ſee) conſiſted of four parts, 1. His <hi>Election,</hi> which preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to the Queen, to be created. 2. His <hi>Confirmation,</hi> which created him Archbiſhop <hi>elect.</hi> Immediately after which, by the ancient Canon-Law, he ſhould have had all ordinary Juriſdiction, (to which was not requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite powers of that <hi>Order</hi> which he wanted, if he wanted any; for any Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man might have been elected to it, (as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> was to <hi>Milan</hi>) and his Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on confirmed) pertaining to that See: namely to Collate Benefices in his gift, to Inſtitute Paſtors, to Licenſe Preachers, to viſit the Province and Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, to call and hold Courts and Synods, inflict or releaſe Cenſures, appoint Chancellors, Vicars Generall, Archdeacons, &amp;c.<note n="(a)">Extra C. tranſmiſſam &amp; C. noſtri, &amp; C. inter corpor. de Tranſlat.</note> But by the later Canons of the Pope (in groſſing all Authority into his own hands) he could not exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe any, though <hi>Conſecrated,</hi> until he had his <hi>Pall</hi> from <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Popes Bull for putting him in <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> of his Church<note n="(b)">Extra Injuctae, de Elect. inter extra comm. &amp; C. Niſi &amp; C. Quod ſicut, &amp;c</note>. And accordingly, the Queen, by the Law of the Land, ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Pope in all his priviledges: and in that among the reſt, he could not, no not after <hi>Conſecration,</hi> exerciſe any Juriſdiction, until by her
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168744:6"/>
Writ, he was put in poſſeſſion of his Biſhoprick. 3. His <hi>Conſecration,</hi> which gave him the Stile, Name, and Dignity of <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> (abſolute.) 4. His <hi>Inſtallation,</hi> which gave him <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> of his Spiritualties. The firſt and laſt of which Acts, were performed by the Dean and Chapter, the two middle moſt by the Biſhops, and the firſt mover of all was the Queen, (or her Chancery.) If I then make it evident, that none of theſe Agents under the Queen, acted in it by any Authority from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but meerly as <hi>the Queens Commiſſioners,</hi> and that ſhe had her Authority for Commiſſionating them, not from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but from the <hi>Parliament:</hi> I hope you will grant it a Demonſtration, that he was no Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> by Authority from Chriſt, but onely of the Parliament. Now all this is eaſily made evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. For as to the <hi>Dean and Chapter,</hi> I am ſure you will grant me that they acted not in it by any Authority from Chriſt: for though you hold <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> to be <hi>de Jure Divino,</hi> you hold not <hi>Deans and Chapters</hi> to be ſo too. The reſt I ſhall prove in the enſuing five Propoſitions.</p>
               <p>The Firſt Propoſition. <hi>Thoſe Biſhops who Confirmed and Conſecrated</hi> Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew Parker, <hi>could not validly do either, by their own Authority, as Biſhops, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Faculty (or Commiſſion) from ſome Superiour in Juriſdiction to the See of</hi> Canterbury. For,</p>
               <p>Firſt, they could not do either validly, as they were Biſhops <hi>Ordine.</hi> For firſt, I ſuppoſe you will grant me, that as Biſhops <hi>Ordine,</hi> they could not <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm</hi> his Election: becauſe that was an act of compleat Juriſdiction, and of giving compleat Juriſdiction, (ſpeaking of that act <hi>per ſe,</hi> or of its own ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal nature, afore it was invalidated by the Popes Law.) Nor ſecondly, for the ſame reaſon could they <hi>Conſecrate</hi> him validly, as Biſhops <hi>Ordine.</hi> For the <hi>Conſecrating</hi> of a Biſhop conſiſted of two parts, or acts. One was the <hi>Sacramental</hi> part: <hi>viz.</hi> the Impoſition of hands by all of them, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing the words of Ordination by one of them in all their names, <hi>[Receive the Holy Ghoſt: and remember to ſtir up the Grace of God which is in thee, by Impoſition of hands, &amp;c.]</hi> And of this Act I will make no queſtion, but they being (as they were) true Biſhops <hi>Ordine,</hi> might, and did, as ſuch, perform it validly, But then, this Act did onely <hi>Ordain him a Biſhop</hi> Ordine, not <hi>Conſecrate him Archbiſhop.</hi> The other part therefore of the Ceremony, (which was all the reſt of it, and from whence the whole Ceremony had its name of <hi>Conſecration</hi>) which may be called the <hi>Sacring</hi> (or the <hi>Ritual</hi>) part, was that which <hi>Conſecrated him Archbiſhop;</hi> to wit, the <hi>Inveſting</hi> of him with his Mitre, Ring, Croſiar-ſtaff, Croſs, Rochet, &amp;c. the <hi>anointing</hi> of his head and hands with <hi>Chriſme,</hi> the pronouncing over him the <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions</hi> proper to an Archbiſhop, and the adhibiting of all theſe Ceremonies with that intent to create him <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> and Paſtor of the Cathedrall and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168744:6"/>
Metropolitical Church, called <hi>Chriſts-Church,</hi> in <hi>Canterbury.</hi> For ſo was their Commiſſion, <hi>[Quatenus eundem in Archiepiſcopum &amp; Paſtorem Eccleſiae Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedralis &amp; Metropoliticae Chriſti Cantuarienſis, Conſecrare, &amp;c.]</hi> And ſo was their demand, when three of them, at his Conſecration, preſented him to the fourth to be Conſecrated: <hi>[Hunc tibi praeſentamus, ut Archiepiſcopus Conſecretur.]</hi> Now this therefore being plainly a meer act of compleat Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction; they could not perform it validly, as Biſhops <hi>Ordine</hi> onely.</p>
               <p>Secondly, they could do neither of theſe acts validly, as they were Biſhops <hi>Officio</hi> (or <hi>Juriſdictione:</hi>) becauſe,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Not one of them was an <hi>actual</hi> Biſhop <hi>Officio.</hi> For, one of them <hi>(Hodgskins)</hi> was onely a Biſhop <hi>Suffragan</hi> of <hi>Dover,</hi> which was no Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral Church, nor could he exerciſe any Juriſdiction but by Commiſſion from the Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> Another of them <hi>(Coverdale)</hi> was onely a <hi>quondam</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exeter.</hi> And the remaining two (<hi>Barlow</hi> and <hi>Sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y</hi>) were ſo alſo, (that is, <hi>quondam</hi> Biſhops onely:) but onely that they were <hi>Elect,</hi> the one to <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> the other to <hi>Hereford.</hi> This appears by the ſtile given them in the Letters Patents: [<hi>Reverendis in Chriſto Patribus, Wilhelmo quondam Bathonienſi &amp; Wellenſi Epiſcopo, nunc Ciceſtrenſi Electo: Joanni quondam Ciceſtrenſi Epiſcopo nunc Electo Herefordenſi: Miloni quon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Exonienſi Epiſcopo, Joanni Epiſcopo Suffraganeo, &amp;c.</hi> That is, <q>To the Reverend Fathers in Chriſt, <hi>William</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells,</hi> now Elect of <hi>Chicheſter: John,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> now Elect of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford: Miles</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Exeter: John</hi> Biſhop Suffragan.]</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. No Biſhop could validly exerciſe any leaſt act of Epiſcopal Juriſdiction (as both theſe were, and of the higheſt nature) out of his own Dioceſs; as <hi>London,</hi> where they <hi>Confirmed,</hi> and <hi>Lambeth</hi> where they <hi>Conſecrated</hi> him, was: and as any place poſſible, muſt have been out of the Dioceſs of all but one of them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. No Biſhop could validly give a Juriſdiction to be exerciſed out of his own Dioceſs; as <hi>Canterbury</hi> was out of all their Dioceſſes.</p>
               <p n="4">4. No Biſhop, nor number of Biſhops (alwayes meaning, <hi>by their own au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi>) could validly give a Juriſdiction greater then their own, and ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to their own, and over themſelves and all the Biſhops in the Land, as that of the See of <hi>Canterbury</hi> was.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Propoſition. [<hi>No Biſhops in the Land could validly Confirm, or Conſecrate an Archbiſhop of</hi> Canterbury <hi>without Commiſſion from the Queen.</hi>] I ſhall give the reaſon in the words of the Statute, 8. <hi>Eliz</hi> 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>all Juriſdiction Spiritual, and Eccleſiaſtical, as by any Spiritual or Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical power or authority, hath hitherto been or may lawfully be uſed over the Eccleſiaſtical State of this Realm, was fully and abſolutely, by the Statute of</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:168744:7"/>
1. Eliz. 1. <hi>united, and annexed to the Imperial Crown of this Realm.</hi> Now it is well known I believe to your ſelf, that afore the Statute of 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8. and after the repeal of that Statute, by Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> until that Act of 1. <hi>Eliz</hi> 1. the Pope had this priviledge in this Realm, that no Biſhops in the Land could validly either Confirm, or Conſecrate an Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> without a Faculty (or Bull) from him: and conſequently, after that Statute, which ſettled all the Popes priviledges in the Crown, that priviledge was in the Queen, that none could do either of thoſe acts without a Faculty from her.</p>
               <p>The third Propoſition. [<hi>The Queen did give Commiſſion to thoſe Biſhops, for the Confirming and Conſecrating of</hi> Matth. Parker.] This appears by the Letters Patents themſelves, extant in the Rolls, in theſe words: [<hi>Elizabetha Regina, &amp;c. Reverendis in Chriſto Patribus, Wilhelmo, &amp;c.</hi> (naming ſeven Biſhops.) <hi>Cùm vacante nuper ſede Archiepiſcopali Cantuarienſi per mortem naturalem D. Reginaldi Poli Cardinalis, ultimi, &amp; immediati Archiepiſcopi &amp; Paſtoris ejusdem; ad humilem petitionem Decani &amp; Capituli Eccleſiae noſtrae Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedralis &amp; Metropoliticae, Chriſti, Cantuarienſis, eiſdem per Literas noſtras Patentes Licentiam conceſſerimus alium ſibi eligendi in Archiepiſcopum &amp; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorem ſedis praedictae, ac iidem</hi> Mattheum Parker <hi>elegerunt, &amp;c Nos eidem electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oni Regium noſtrum aſſenſum adhibuimus pariter &amp; favorem. Et hoc vobis tenore praeſentium ſignificamus: Rogantes, ac in fide &amp; dilectione quibus nobis tenemini, firmiter praecipiendo, Mandantes, quatenus vos, aut quatuor veſtrûm, cundem</hi> Matheum Parker <hi>in Archiepiſcopum &amp; Paſtorem Eccleſiae praedictae Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum, electionemque praedictam, Confirmare, &amp; eundem in Archiepiſcopum &amp; Paſtorem Eccleſiae praedictae Conſecrare, caeteraque omnia peragere, quae veſtro in hac parte incumbunt Officio Paſtorali, juxta formam Statutorum in ea parte editorum &amp; proviſorum, velitis cum effectu.</hi> That is. <q>
                     <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Queen, &amp;c. To the Reverend Fathers in Chriſt, <hi>William, &amp;c.</hi> Whereas the Archiepiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal See of <hi>Canterbury</hi> being lately void by the natural death of my Lord <hi>Reginald Pool</hi> Cardinal, the laſt and immediate Archbiſhop and Paſtor of it; at the humble petition of the Dean and Chapter of our Cathedral and Metropolitical Church in <hi>Canterbury,</hi> called <hi>Chriſts Church,</hi> we did by our Letters Patents grant Licence to them to chuſe themſelves another for Archbiſhop and Paſtor of the See aforeſaid, and they have choſen <hi>Matthew Parker,</hi> &amp;c. We have given our royal aſſent and favour to the ſaid Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And we ſignifie this to you by the tenor of theſe preſents. Requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and by the fidelity and love wherein you are bound to us, firmly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning, Commanding you, that you, or four of you, effectually Confirm the ſaid <hi>Matthew Parker</hi> Archbiſhop and Paſtor Elect of the ſaid Church, and Confirm the ſaid Election, and Conſecrate him Archbiſhop and Paſtor
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168744:7"/>
of the ſaid Church, and do all other things which in this behalf are incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent on your Paſtoral Office, according to the form of the Statutes in this caſe made and provided.]</q>
               </p>
               <p>And further, for the avoiding of all ambiguities and queſtions that might be objected againſt the lawful Confirming and Conſecrating of the ſaid <hi>Matthew Parker:</hi> (partly becauſe the Popes conſent (without which all was void and null by the Canon Law eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in generall Councels<note n="(a)">
                     <hi>But univerſally this is clear, that if any one be made a Biſhop, without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of his Metropolitane, the great Synod hath defined, that ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>one ought not to be a Biſhop,</hi> (meaning by <hi>Biſhop,</hi> any Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop whatſoever, and principally the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate</hi> of a Nation; and by <hi>Metropolitane,</hi> meaning any Metropolitane whatſoever, but principally the <hi>Patriarch</hi> of that part of the world, which you grant the Pope to be of the Weſt.) Conc. Nic. 1 Can. 6.</note> which you count the proper Rule for judging, even againſt Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, in theſe matters,<note n="(b)">Councils truly General, being the ſupream Tribunals of the Catholique Church, do binde particular Churches, as well in point of diſcipline, as of faith. Biſh. of <hi>Derr. ſchiſm gard.</hi> p. 475. Engliſh Statutes cannot change the eſſentials of ordination: the vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity or invalidity of it, depends not upon hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Law, but upon the Inſtitution of Chriſt. <hi>id.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. p. 41. Judges at the Common Law, have neither grounds nor rules in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law for judging of the validity of an Epiſcopal Conſecration, <hi>id. ib.</hi> p. 60.</note> was not to it; and partly becauſe none of thoſe who Confirmed or Conſecrated him was an actual Biſhop) it was judged (by her Council, and by thoſe Lawyers, Civil, and Canon, who were adviſed with in it) needful ſhe ſhould inſert into her Patent, a clauſe, whereby by her ſupream royal autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſhe ſhould enable thoſe Biſhops, in regard of the preſent exigencies (becauſe neither the Popes conſent nor actual Biſhops enough to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate him, could be had,) to ſupply to themſelves all defects whatſoever, in quality, faculty, or any other things neceſſary to that performance, by the Laws of the Church. For ſo it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows in the Patent. [<hi>Supplentes nihilominus ſuprema authoritate noſtra Regia, ſiquid in vobis, aut veſtrum aliquo, conditione, ſtatu, aut facultate veſtris, ad praemiſſa perficienda deſit eorum quae per Statuta hujus Regni noſtri, aut per Leges Eccleſiaſticas, in hac parte requiruntur aut neceſſaria ſunt; temporis ratione, &amp; rerum neceſſitate, id poſtulante.</hi> That is, <q>Supplying nevertheleſs (to your ſelves) by our ſupream Regal Authority <hi>(hereby delegated to you to that end)</hi> if any thing, in you, or any one of you, or in your condition, ſtate, or faculty, to the performing of the Premiſes, is wanting of thoſe things which by the Statutes of this our Realm, or by the Eccleſiaſtical Laws, are in this behalf requiſite or neceſſary: the condition of the time, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of things requiring it.]</q> So you ſee how true it was I ſaid, they could do neither of thoſe Acts without her Commiſſion; when not onely her <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi> was judged neceſſary to give them power to do them, but her <hi>Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:168744:8"/>
alſo, to make their acts valid, <hi>non obſtante,</hi> the Laws of the Church.</p>
               <p>The fourth Propoſition. <hi>[The Queens Letters Patents was not a meer Mandate, commanding them to execute their Office, which they might be ſuppoſed to have from Chriſt, but a Commiſſion, authorizing them to do what they did; ſo as they acted in it, not as Biſhops, (or Officers authorized by Chriſt) but meerly as her Commiſſioners.]</hi> That in that quality onely they <hi>Confirmed</hi> him, themſelves expreſly acknowledge and declare in the Inſtrument of his Confirmation, (as it is to be ſeen in the Records at <hi>Lambeth.</hi>) For thus they ſay, [<hi>In nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Domini, Amen. Nos</hi> Wilhelmus Barlow, <hi>&amp;c. Mediantibus Literis Commiſſionalibus Reginae, Commiſſionarii ſpecialiter &amp; legitime deputati, &amp;c. praedictam electionem</hi> Mathei Parker <hi>in Archiepiſcopum &amp; Paſtorem Eccleſiae prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictae, ſuprema authoritate Regiâ nobis in hac parte Commiſſa, Confirmamus. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plentes ex ſuprema authoritate Regiâ nobis delegata, quicquid in nobis, aut alique</hi> &amp;c, <hi>ut ſupra.</hi> That is, <q>In the name of the Lord, Amen. We, <hi>William,</hi> &amp;c. By the Queens Commiſſional Letters, ſpecially, and lawfully deputed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, &amp;c. do by the ſupreme authority of the Queen to us, in this behalf, committed, Confirm the aforeſaid Election of <hi>Mat. Parker,</hi> &amp;c. ſupplying, by the ſupreme authority of the Queen, to us delegated, if any thing be wanting in us, or any of us, &amp;c. <hi>as above.</hi>]</q> And if as her Commiſſioners they <hi>Confirmed,</hi> as her Commiſſioners alſo they <hi>Conſecrated</hi> him. For, 1. The Patent Commiſſionates them to both alike, and they needed her Commiſſion to both alike. [<hi>Mandantes quatenus eundem Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mare, &amp; Conſecrare velitis, &amp;c.</hi> 
                  <q>Commanding you that you Confirm and Conſecrate him.]</q> So if <hi>Mandantes</hi> did authoriſe them to the one, it did ſo to the other alſo. 2. The Patent did, in formal words, <hi>authoriſe</hi> them to diſpenſe with themſelves for any defect of Faculty, &amp;c. for the performing of both thoſe acts alike: <hi>[Supplentes, ſuprema authoritate noſtra Regia, ſi quid, ad praemiſſa perficienda, deeſt, &amp;c.]</hi> And this Diſpenſation was neceſſary to the validity of both thoſe acts alike. 3. To ſignifie they did Conſecrate him in vertue of the Queens Commiſſion to them for it, when three of them, at the performing of that Ceremony, preſented him to the fourth, to be Conſecrated; whereas (afore the Statute of <hi>H.</hi> 8.) the Popes Bull for authoriſing the Conſecrators, was uſed to be read, at that time; in place thereof was read the Queens Patent to them. [<hi>Proferebatur</hi> (ſaith the Act of it, upon <hi>Parkers</hi> Records) <hi>Regium Mandatum pro ejus Conſecratione, &amp;.</hi> 
                  <q>The Queens Mandate (or Commiſſion) to them for Conſecrating of him was read.]</q> as the authority for what they did.</p>
               <p>The fifth and laſt Propoſition. <hi>[The Queen had her Authority for Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating them, from the Parliament.]</hi> This is manifeſt.</p>
               <p>Firſt, from the Statute of 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8.20. which recites how that by an Act
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168744:8"/>
made that Parliament, they had enacted [<hi>That if any perſon nominated or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the King to the See of</hi> Rome, <hi>to be any Archbiſhop of this Realm ſhould be delayed, denied, or otherwiſe diſturbed from the ſame, for lack of Palls, Bulls, or other things to him requiſite</hi> (by the Law of the Land then in force) <hi>to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of the See of</hi> Rome; <hi>that then he might and ſhould be Conſecrated, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted by any two Biſhops in this Realm, appointed by the King.</hi>] Where although in the next words, <hi>[according, and after like manner, as divers Archbiſhops and Biſhops have been heretofore in ancient time, by ſundry of the Kings Progenitors, made, Conſecrated, and Inveſted within this Realm:]</hi> they were willing to ſeem as if they did not then firſt <hi>grant</hi> that right or priviledge to the Crown, but onely <hi>reſtore</hi> it: yet it is manifeſt they did then <hi>grant</hi> it to him. For, as they named none, ſo nor could they name any one King of <hi>England,</hi> who <hi>made</hi> a Biſhop within this Realm, and much leſs (the Primate of <hi>England</hi>) the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> Indeed <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour, <hi>Rufus,</hi> and <hi>Hen.</hi> 1. (and perhaps ſome of our Kings afore them) did without asking the Popes conſent, <hi>Inveſt</hi> Biſhops, in vacant Sees; that is, by the delivery of a <hi>Ring,</hi> and <hi>Croſiar,</hi> did put them in poſſeſſion of their Biſhopricks, ſo as to injoy their Temporalties, and to be legal Biſhops in the Kings Courts. But I know no inſtance of one Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury, Inveſted</hi> by any one of them, without the Popes conſent; nor did any of them uſe that pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of <hi>Inveſting</hi> Biſhops, after the Council of <hi>Vienna</hi> (which was in the time of <hi>Edw.</hi> 2.) had prohibited it to all Lay perſons, under excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion both to them that did it, and to the Biſhops that accepted it. Which their deſiſting to uſe it after that time, and the Parliaments ſilence in it, (who were at that time very active, and full of animoſity, in vindicating the rights of the Crown, againſt the Popes uſurpations and incroachments) ſeems to acknowledge, that thoſe who had done it before, had done it <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facto</hi> onely, and not of right. But however it were for that of <hi>Inveſting:</hi> it is certain, all our Hiſtories will not afford one Inſtance of any King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who <hi>appointed,</hi> or <hi>aſſigned</hi> (that is, in the ſenſe of the Statute, <hi>authorized</hi>) Biſhops, to <hi>Conſecrate</hi> a Biſhop. So, without all peradventure, this priviledge was plainly <hi>granted</hi> to the Crown by this Statute. And it was granted him at firſt, onely in caſe of the Popes refractorineſs; but ſoon after, by the Statute aforenamed, all recourſe to <hi>Rome</hi> for <hi>Confirmation,</hi> or <hi>Conſecration,</hi> of any Biſhop, was forbidden, and the power of authorizing Biſhops within the Realm to perform thoſe acts, was placed abſolutely in the King. <q>[Whereas in the ſaid act (meaning, that afore ſpoken of) it is not plainly expreſſed in what manner Archbiſhops and Biſhops ſhall be Inveſted, and Conſecrated, within the Realm: be it now therefore enacted by the authority of this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament that no perſon ſhall be preſented to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor ſhall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168744:9"/>
ſend, nor procure there for any manner of Bulls, Palls, or other things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for an Archbiſhop, Biſhop, &amp;c. And if the perſon be elected to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of an Archbiſhop, after ſuch Election certified to the King, he ſhall be reputed Lord Elect to the ſaid Office. And the King ſhall by his Letters Patents ſignifie the ſaid Election to one Archbiſhop, and two other Biſhops, or elſe to four Biſhops within this Realm, to be aſſigned by the King, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring or commanding him or them to Confirm the ſaid Election, and to Inveſt and Conſecrate the ſaid perſon ſo elected, to the Office and Dignity that he is elected unto, and to give and uſe to him, ſuch Pall, Benedictions, and other Ceremonies, as formerly were uſed. And every perſon being hereafter Inveſted and Conſecrated to the Dignity or Office of any Archbiſhop, according to the tenor of this Act, ſhall and may be Inthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized, and Inſtalled, &amp;c. and ſhall be obeyed, &amp;c. and ſhall do and execute in every thing and things, touching the ſame, as any Archbiſhop of this Realm, (without offending the Prerogative Royal, and the Laws and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms of this Realm) might at any time heretofore do.]</q>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, from the Statute of 8. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. made purpoſely to ſet forth the Authority, (next under God) by which <hi>Mathew Parker,</hi> and the other firſt Proteſtant Biſhops in the beginning of the Queens Reign were made: and ſets it forth, by reciting how they were made by authority of the Queen, and how ſhe was authorized to that end, by the aforeſaid Statute of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and by the Statute of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. Theſe are the words of it, for as much as concerns my purpoſe. <q>[Foraſmuch as divers queſtions hath lately grown upon the making and Conſecrating of Archbiſhops and Biſhops within this Realm, whether the ſame were duly and orderly done, according to the Law or not, which is much tending to the ſlander of all the ſtate of the Clergy, being one of the greateſt States of this Realm; therefore for the avoiding of ſuch ſlanderous ſpeech, and to the end that every man that is willing to know the truth, may plainly underſtand, that the ſame evil ſpeech and talk is not grounded upon any iuſt matter or cauſe: It is thought convenient hereby partly to touch ſuch author<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ties as do allow and approve the making and Conſecrating of the ſame Archbiſhops and Biſhops to be duly and orderly done, according to the Laws of this Realm. Firſt, it is very well known to all degrees of this Realm, that the late King <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. was as well by all the Clergy then of this Realm in their ſeverall Convocations, as alſo by all the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in divers of his Parliaments, juſtly and rightfully recognized and knowledged to have the Supream Power, Juriſdiction, and Authority over the Eccleſiaſtical State of the ſame. And that the ſaid King did by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Parliament in the twenty fifth year of his Reign, ſet forth a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168744:9"/>
order of the manner and form how Archbiſhops and Biſhops ſhould be made, &amp;c. And although in the time of the late Queen, the ſaid Act was repealed, yet nevertheleſs at the Parliament 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. the ſaid Act was revived; and by one other Act there made, all ſuch Juriſdictions, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, &amp;c. Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtical, as by any Spiritual or Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Power or Authority hath heretofore been, or may lawfully be uſed over the Eccleſiaſticall State of this Realm, is fully and abſolutely, by the Authority of the ſame Parliament, united and annexed to the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Crown of this Realm. And by the ſame Statute, there is alſo gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Queen (mark, <hi>given alſo to the Queen by that Statute</hi>) full Power and Authority, by Letters Patents, to aſſign, and authorize ſuch perſon or perſons as ſhe ſhall think meet,</q> 
                  <hi>(whether Biſhops, Noblemen, Lawyers, Merchants, or who ever elſe, ſo they be NAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RAL BORN S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BJECTS; for the words of that Statute requires no other Qualification to them but that)</hi> 
                  <q>to exerciſe under her all manner of Juriſdiction in any wiſe touching or concerning any Spiritual Juriſdiction within this Realm. Whereupon <hi>(that is, upon the Authority given to her by this Act)</hi> the Queen having in her order and diſpoſition all the ſaid Juriſdiction, &amp;c. <hi>(that is, all that which formerly was in the Pope)</hi> hath, by her Supream Authority, cauſed divers to be duly made and Conſecrated Archbiſhops and Biſhops, according to ſuch order and form, and with ſuch Ceremonies in and about their Conſecration, as were allowed and ſet forth by the ſaid Acts, &amp;c. And further, for the avoiding of all ambiguities and queſtions might be objected againſt the lawfull Confirming, Inveſting, and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crating of the ſaid Archbiſhops and Biſhops, her Highneſſe hath (in her Letters Patents) uſed divers ſpeciall words, whereby, by her Supream Authority, ſhe hath diſpenſed with all cauſes and doubts of any Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, or diſability, &amp;c. So that to all thoſe that will well conſider of the effect and true intent of the ſaid Statutes, and of the Supream and abſolute Authority of the Queen, <hi>(granted to her by them)</hi> and which ſhe, by her ſaid Letters Patents, hath uſed in and about the making and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrating of the ſaid Archbiſhops and Biſhops, it is and may be very evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, no cauſe of doubt can or may juſtly be objected againſt the ſaid Confirmations and Conſecrations, &amp;c.]</q> Loe here declared, by the Queen her ſelf, by <hi>Matthew Parker</hi> himſelf, and all the other Biſhops then in the Land, and by all the Lords Temporall, and the Commons in Parliament, that <hi>Matthew Parker</hi> was made, Confirmed and Conſecrated Archbiſhop, by Authority of the Queen, and that ſhe had her Authority for it from the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:168744:10"/>3. From that Clauſe in the Commiſſion it ſelf, for the <hi>Confirming</hi> and <hi>Conſecrating</hi> of <hi>Matthew Parker,</hi> wherein ſhe expreſly refers to the Statutes made in that behalf, meaning thoſe two aforenamed. [<hi>Juxta formam</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>Statutorum in ea parte proviſorum &amp; editorum. According to the form of the Statutes in this caſe made and ſet forth.</hi>] As much as to ſay, that the Patent was grounded upon thoſe Statutes.</p>
               <p>And ſo I have abundantly demonſtrated my Theſis, as to you, <hi>[That you have no Authority to preach, but what you have originally from the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.]</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:168744:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſecond Part.</hi> Demonſtrating to a Presbyterian Miniſter, that he hath no Authority to preach from Chriſt, but onely from the Parliament,</head>
               <p>SIr, I ſhall ſuppoſe your Caſe the beſt that can be ſuppoſed of any <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi> Miniſter in <hi>England; viz.</hi> That <hi>William Juxon</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> being a true Presbyter, together with all the Presbyters then of <hi>London</hi> aſſiſting him, Ordained twelve Presbyters, whom after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he placed as Paſtors, or preaching Miniſters, in ſo many Pariſh Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in <hi>London</hi> lying next to one another. Theſe twelve preaching Miniſters were the firſt Claſſical Presbytery, that after the aboliſhing of Biſhops, was erected in the Nation. And the Church of <hi>N.</hi> within the Precinct of that Claſſis, falling void, they <hi>Ordained</hi> you a Presbyter, and afterward gave you <hi>Miſſion</hi> to that Congregation of <hi>N.</hi> (that is, placed you to be the Paſtor or preaching Miniſter of it) And I ſay, that in this Caſe, <hi>you have no authority to preach to that Congregation from Chriſt, but onely from the Parliament.</hi> And I make it good by this Argument.</p>
               <p>You have no Authority from Chriſt to preach to that Congregation, but what you have either by your <hi>Ordination,</hi> or your <hi>Miſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But you have <hi>no</hi> Authority to preach to that Congregation by your <hi>Ordination:</hi> and none from <hi>him,</hi> but from the Parliament onely, by your <hi>Miſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore you have none from him, but onely from the Parliament.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is ſuppoſed in the Caſe: nor is there any third ordinary way imaginable, and you pretend not to extraordinary.</p>
               <p>The firſt part of the <hi>Minor, [That you have no Authority to preach to that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation by your Ordination]</hi> I prove from the form of it; which (ſuppoſing it the ſame as is preſcribed in your <hi>Directory</hi>) was this. The Presbytery of that Claſſis laid their hands upon you, accompanying it with a ſhort Prayer, or
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168744:11"/>
Bleſſing, by the Preacher who carried on the Work of that day, to this effect: [<hi>Thankefully acknowledging, &amp;c. for fitting and inclining this man to this great work, we beſeech him to fill him with his holy Spirit, (whom in his name</hi> (here they laid their hands upon you) <hi>we ſet apart to this holy Service) to fulfill the work of his Miniſtery in all things, that he may ſave both himſelf, and his people committed to his charge.</hi>] In which words (added to the Impoſition of hands, to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret the meaning of it, that it might not be a dumb Ceremony) you ſee there is not one ſyllable of authorizing you to preach to that Congregation of <hi>N.</hi> but onely that they who laid their hands on you, <hi>ſet you apart to this great and holy work and office of the Miniſtery;</hi> that is, that by, in, or with that Impoſition of hands, there was given to you from and by Chriſt himſelf im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, a divine <hi>power</hi> lawfully to execute the Office of preaching, and miniſtring Sacraments in Chriſts name, and with his authority, to that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation unto which you were then deſigned, or to any other in the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or in the world, whereunto you ſhould be duly admitted. And that this <hi>power</hi> (I ſpeak of) was all that theſe words, or the Impoſition of bands, gave you and not any <hi>Authority</hi> as to that Congregation of <hi>N.</hi> is manifeſt; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if they gave you <hi>Authority</hi> to that Congregation, it was either to that Congregation <hi>alone,</hi> or to <hi>more</hi> then that. If to that <hi>alone,</hi> you could not be admitted as Miniſter to any other Congregation, without being anew Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained: which you count neither neceſſary, nor lawful.<note n="(a)">If a Miniſter be deſigned to a Congregation, who hath been formerly Ordained Presbyter; let him be admitted after examination, without any new Ordination.</note> And if to <hi>more</hi> then that, it muſt be to any (or every) one in the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and in the world; becauſe the words name none, nor mean no one more then another, and authorized you as much to every one, as to any one: or elſe when you ſhould be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Officiate in any Congregation, neither you nor the people could be certain, whether that were one of the Congregations or no, to which your Ordination authorized you: which uncertainty would render it uſeleſs as to any one. And if you ſay, your Ordination authorized you to every one, you would be a Paſtor <hi>Apoſtolique,</hi> (or ſuch a one as the Apoſtles were) that is, <hi>univerſal,</hi> created by Chriſt <hi>immediately,</hi> and conſequently <hi>ſupream,</hi> (ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to no Claſſis, Synod, Parliament, or other mortal ſuperiour) which would utterly overthrow all your form of Church Government and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline. For then you might preach and miniſter Sacraments in any Church, where you ſhould pleaſe, againſt the Paſtors will; then all <hi>Admiſſions</hi> of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters to be preaching Miniſters to ſuch or ſuch a Church, would be vain, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, and arrogant acts: Then no Claſſis, Synod, or Parliament, could for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168744:11"/>
any crime whatſoever, convent, or ſilence you, and much leſs depoſe or eject you. In fine, then there would be no diſtinction betwixt Paſtors and flocks. Of neceſſity therefore, to avoid ſuch horrid abſurdities, the firſt part of my <hi>minor</hi> muſt be granted me, <hi>[That you have no authority, by your Ordination, to preach in that Congregation.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond part of the <hi>Minor, [That you have no authority from Chriſt, but onely from the Parliament, by your Miſſion.]</hi> I thus make good.</p>
               <p>They who gave you your Miſſion had no Authority from Chriſt, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the Parliament, to give it you.</p>
               <p>Therefore you have no Authority from Chriſt, but onely from the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by your Miſſion.</p>
               <p>The Conſequence is evident in the terms. The Antecedent is firm, for two reaſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe thoſe Presbyters who gave you Miſſion, were no Miniſters of thoſe Churches, by any <hi>Divine Right,</hi> or Authority from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but onely of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> becauſe placed in thoſe Churches by the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> as he was <hi>Biſhop of London:</hi> which I am ſure you will not, cannot, dare not ſay he was by authority from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (for then it had been a wicked and ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious act in the Parliament to deprive him of his Biſhoprick; and in you, to adviſe and encourage them to it) nor by any other Authority but that of the Parliament; for then it had exceeded the power of the Parliament to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive him of it. Nor can you ſay, thoſe Miniſters were placed in thoſe Churches by him in any other quality or capacity, but as he was <hi>Biſhop of London:</hi> becauſe as he was a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> he could not Inſtitute Paſtors by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alone, as he did thoſe; nor Inſtitute them in any wiſe, as a Biſhop <hi>Ordine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe ſuppoſing they had been Miniſters of thoſe Churches by Authority from Chriſt; yet as they were <hi>ſingle</hi> Presbyters, they had no autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſo much as to <hi>Ordain,</hi> and much leſs to give <hi>Miſſion,</hi> but onely as they were <hi>Aſſociated</hi> into a <hi>Claſſis,</hi> (or <hi>Presbytery.</hi>)<note n="(a)">
                     <hi>Preaching Miniſters, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly Aſſociated, are thoſe to whom Impoſition of hands doth appertain.</hi> Humb. Adv. of Div. at Weſtm. in the Doctr. part of Ordin. §. 10.</note> Now this <hi>Aſſociation</hi> was not made, formed, or authorized by any authority from Chriſt, but onely of the Parliament: and ſo thoſe Miniſters who gave you your Miſſion, did not give it you as <hi>Presbyters</hi> or <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> inſtituted by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but meerly as Officers or Commiſſioners of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> (which it was by accident, that any of them were <hi>Presbyters.</hi>) This appears,</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe for Aſſociating the <hi>firſt</hi> Presbytery, there was no other ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable (ordinary) Authority then in the Land, but that of the Parliament. And if you will ſay, the <hi>firſt</hi> was Aſſociated by Chriſt <hi>immediately;</hi> any
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168744:12"/>
of thoſe whom you call <hi>Sectaries,</hi> ſay as much for their authority, and with as much reaſon.</p>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe it appears by the Ordinances, Acts, and publick Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Parliament, by you owned and abetted, in aboliſhing the form of Church Government and Diſcipline then eſtabliſhed, and introducing an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in place thereof; in ſettling Claſſes, and authorizing them to Ordain Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters; in ejecting Miniſters, and placing others in their Cures; in Collating, and Inſtituting to vacant Benefices; and executing theſe powers not by Presbyters onely, but by Lay-Committees, nay, by ſingle Lords and Officers of the Army, &amp;c. that the ſupream viſible Authority in matters Eccleſiaſtical in this Land was in the Parliament: and ſo no Claſſis was Aſſociated but by authority of the Parliament, and after its Aſſociation, had no authority to give Miſſion, or exerciſe any other act of Juriſdiction, but what it had from the Parliament.</p>
               <p>For Inſtance I name theſe Ordinances.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That of 12. <hi>June,</hi> 1643. <q>[Whereas it hath been declared and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Lords and Commons in Parliament, that the preſent Church Government, by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, &amp;c. is evil, &amp;c. and that therefore they are reſolved that the ſame ſhall be taken away, and that ſuch a Government ſhall be ſettled in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as may be moſt agreeable to Gods Word, &amp;c. the right Honourable <hi>Algernon Percy,</hi> Earl of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>(naming other Earls and Lords) John Selden, Dr. Gouge,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>(naming divers others Lawyers, Gentlemen, and Divines)</hi> are hereby authorized and enjoyned to ſit, confer, and treat of ſuch things as concern the Diſcipline and Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as ſhall be propoſed to them by both, or either Houſe of Parliament, &amp;c Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that they aſſume not to exerciſe any Juriſdiction Eccleſiaſtical whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, or any other power then is particularly expreſſed.]</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That of 22. <hi>January</hi> following. <q>[The Earl of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> ſhall have authority in the aſſociated Counties, to eject all ſuch Miniſters as he ſhall judge unfit for their places, and to place in their rooms ſuch as ſhall be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of by the Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>]</q>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. That of 22. <hi>Feb.</hi> following. <q>[The Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> ſhall nominate and appoint ſuch able and godly Divines as he ſhall think fit, into all ſuch Churches in the County of <hi>York,</hi> as are, or ſhall be deſtitute of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. That of 23. <hi>April</hi> 1645. <q>[<hi>Philip Goodwin</hi> ſhall be henceforth Vicar of <hi>Watford,</hi> and Officiate the Cure as Vicar thereof, during his life, without any further Admiſſion or Induction.]</q>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:168744:12"/>5. That of 26. <hi>April</hi> following. <q>[None may preach, but Ordained Miniſters, except ſuch as intending the Miniſtery ſhall for trial of their Gifts be allowed by ſuch as ſhall be appointed by the Parliament.]</q>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. That of 29. <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1648. <q>[Be it Ordained by the Authority of this Parliament, that all Pariſhes in this Nation ſhall be brought under the Government of Congregational, Provincial, and National Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, &amp;c. And all Claſſes, and Parochial Congregations, are reſpectively hereby authorized and required to proceed accordingly, &amp;c. The Province of <hi>London</hi> ſhall be divided into twelve Claſſical Elderſhips. The firſt Claſſis to contain <hi>Alhallows,</hi> &amp;c. The ſeveral Claſſes where no Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational Presbyteries are already ſettled, ſhall have power to nominate ſuch Miniſters and others as are qualified according to this Ordinance, to joyn with them in the ſame, to be approved by the Committee of Lords and Commons for Scandal, until ſuch time as Congregational Presbyteries ſhall be ſettled in the ſaid reſpective Precincts, &amp;c. When ſeven Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational Elderſhips or more ſhall be conſtituted into any Claſſical Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct, the ſame ſhall be ſignified to the ſeveral Congregational Elders ſo eſtabliſhed, who ſhall depute fit Elders, who, together with their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, ſhall meet as a Claſſis, &amp;c. That which ſhall be done by the major part of the Claſſis, ſhall be eſteemed as the act of the whole. And none ſhall be eſteemed a valid act, unleſs done by four Miniſters, and eight Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Elders, &amp;c. The power of Claſſicall Aſſemblies, ſhall be: 1. To Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, and admit Miniſters for the Congregations. 2. To cenſure Miniſters, &amp;c. It is Ordained by the Authority of this Parliament, that the Claſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Presbyters within their Bounds may and ſhall Ordain Presbyters, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Directory for Ordination hereafter expreſſed, &amp;c. The Presbytery, or five Miniſters at leaſt ſent from them, ſhall ſolemnly ſet him who is to be Ordained, apart to the Office and work of the Miniſtery, &amp;c. Laying their hands on him, with a ſhort Prayer or Bleſſing to this effect, &amp;c. Let every one which is or ſhall be choſen for any Congregation or place not being at that time within the Bounds of any Claſſical Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, be Ordained by that Claſſis which he ſhall addreſs himſelf unto, &amp;c. And it is further Ordained by the Authority Aforeſaid, That all perſons who ſhall be Ordained Presbyters, according to this Directory, ſhall be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever reputed, to all intents, for lawfull, and ſufficiently authorized Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, &amp;c.]</q>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, It appears from the humble Advice of your Divines aſſembled at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> unto the Parliament (afore any Claſſes were formed) to <hi>authorize</hi> Miniſters to <hi>Aſſociate</hi> themſelves into Claſſes, for the Ordaining
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168744:13"/>
of Miniſters, for the Army, Navy, City of <hi>London,</hi> &amp;c. <q>[In theſe preſent exigencies, while we cannot have any Presbyteries form'd up to their whole power and work, &amp;c. And yet it is requiſite that Miniſters be Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for the ſervice of places and Congregations deſtitute of Miniſters, by ſome who being ſet apart themſelves for the work of the Miniſtery, have power to joyn in the ſetting apart of others: Let ſome Miniſters in or about <hi>London</hi> be deſigned BY PUBLIQUE AUTHORITY, <hi>(meaning, of the Parliament, to which they addreſſed that Advice)</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ASSOCIATED, may Ordain Miniſters for the City, and vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, &amp;c. And let the like ASSOCIATION, be made BY THE SAME AUTHORITY, in other Counties, &amp;c.]</q>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo I have abundantly demonſtrated my Theſis, <hi>[That you have no Authority to preach in that Church of</hi> N. <hi>(where you are Miniſter) from Chriſt, but from the Parliament onely.]</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
